Hi, I'm Lilach Bullock.
I'm the Conversion Optimization Faculty
Chair for Simplilearn. I'm also Digital
Marketing Consultant, Social Media
Expert, special speaker, and best-selling
author. I started my first business,
Asklilach, in 2006 and grew it
from just me to having offices and
employing staff. I got to work with some
fabulous people and even went to Downing
Street as a finalist for the best MumPreneur of the year.
Welcome to the Advanced
Conversion Optimization course.
I understand the struggle to make online
business work for you. I've been there
and done that and that is why I want to
help you to show you what really works,
to give you the shortcuts, the processes
and systems, and insight you need so that,
you can make the online world work for
you in the way that it has worked for me,
so that you can get the results that you
need to grow your business. If you're not
doing digital right, then it really can
feel like a drain on your resources. Are
you spending money, time, and resources
with very little to show for it? I want
to show you a better way and help you do
it right. There's no value in driving
traffic to your website if that traffic
doesn't convert. More conversions mean
more revenue and, is what you are really
interested in. In this lesson, we will
start by defining Conversion
Optimization and then explain why it is
important to optimize your website for
conversions. By the end of this lesson,
you will have a good understanding of
the meaning of Conversion Optimization
and the difference optimizing a website
can make to the online success of your
business. Let's get started and discover
how Conversion Optimization can make a
real difference to your business. A
simple definition of Conversion Rate
Optimization can be found on Wikipedia,
which describes Conversion Rate
Optimization as, "A system for increasing
the percentage of visitors to a website
that convert into customers, or more
generally, take any desired action on a
webpage.
It is commonly referred to as CRO."
What does this mean in practice? Let's
start by considering two websites. They
appear identical in every way, they have
the same amount of daily traffic, the
same web copy, and at the start, the same
conversion rate. Let's assume that they
convert at 2%, that means, that out of
every 100 visitors to the website, two of
them will make it all the way through
the sales process and actually end up
buying something from the website. If just
2% of visitors are purchasing from the
website, that means that all of the
site's revenue is coming from just 2% of
the traffic. Now suppose, that one of
these websites starts to implement
Conversion Optimization strategies. Both
of the websites continue to receive the
same amount of traffic, so there is no
difference in the amount of money being
spent to promote the site. The only
difference is, in what happens once the
visitor reaches the website. The good
news here is that that means that all of
these issues are directly under the
control of the website owner. After a few
months of consistently working to
optimize one of the websites, it should be
possible to see that, while website A is
still converting at 2%, website B is now
converting at 3%. You may be thinking
that a 1% difference in a conversion
rate doesn't sound like very much, but
think about it in terms of absolute
figures. How much traffic does your own
website receive in an average month? If
you average 10,000 website visitors each
month, a 2% conversion rate will bring
you 200 sales. With the same traffic
figures, a 3% conversion rate
will produce 300 sales, that's an extra
100 sales on your website with no extra
work, or promoting your website. What sort
of changes can produce these results?
Conversion Optimization isn't
necessarily about making big changes. It
is more usually about making small
incremental changes over an extended
time that can lead to big results and a
substantial increase in revenue
over time. It might be that just altering
a single image, or one line of text could
increase your conversion rate to the
point that you end up making millions of
pounds more over time. Conversion
Optimization isn't a one-off process, it
needs to be thought of as an ongoing
operation. You make a change, and then
test that change to see how effective it
has been. Over time, you'll find out what
changes work and what doesn't work. Some
changes you might make, actually reduce
your conversion rate. If you find out
what has happened, don't panic, you
now know what doesn't work, you just need
to find out why it doesn't work and then
you will be in a much stronger position
to make the changes that will result in
higher conversions and a growth in
revenue. Throughout this course, we are
going to look at how you can take the
principles of Conversion Optimization
and apply them so that you can take
control of your website traffic and
transform those visitors into real sales,
or leads, or subscribers, or whatever you
want to do with those people who are
viewing your website. We will look at
each of the ways customers interact with
your website and see how we can optimize
each of them to maximize the benefits of
each of them to you. Why should you worry
about Conversion Optimization, even if
your website conversion rate is in gray,
can't you just get more traffic just by
paying for a few extra adverts and
bringing an extra sale that way? What's
the advantage of the Conversion
Optimization approach compared to simply
driving more traffic and getting more
sales that way? The best answer is that
Conversion Optimization works
better and will ultimately produce
better results for your business. By
improving your conversion rate, you
improve the quality of your business. You
build a stronger connection with your
visitors, as more of them go on to
become your customers. You improve the
public perception of your business, as
more of those that read your website, are
left with a favorable impression that
your business is useful to them. On top
of all of these benefits, you ultimately,
reduce your expenses as you now have to
buy less adverts, you increase your
productivity and your overall market
share as your
business grows. How are all of these
results achieved? By focusing on
continuous improvement, make more of your
traffic profitable. So, your advertising
budget will stretch further and provide
a better overall experience for
customers. Who makes the decisions in
your business?
What do they base these decisions on? Often
in a business, what you will find is, that
the person at the top makes all the
decisions, and getting their approval is
essential for any plan to move forward.
They will make their final decision for
any of a variety of reasons. It may be
that, they will examine all of the data
on a given subject and then follow what
the data says they should do. Or perhaps,
they are one of those managers that
bases their decision on the way that
they feel at the time of their own
personal experience. They use their gut
instinct as the basis for their decision.
Understanding how those decisions are
made, will help when it comes to
discussing the changes that will have to
come to your business, if you're going to
take Conversion Optimization seriously.
There is a lot of data to look at, in
Conversion Optimization. You could spend
weeks working through the analytics, and
seeing where people left your website
and why they didn't convert. You need to
try to empathize with your customers and
think about how they are responding to
your website. It is this balancing act,
that you must successfully complete if
you are to truly master Conversion
Optimization. To do this, there are
probably going to have to be some big
changes to the way your company thinks.
The customer experience must become
central to everything you do, perhaps you
think this is already true for your
business. But in my experience, when you
really start to examine the facts, it's
rarely the case. We will look at what you
can do one step at a time, to
revolutionize the way you do business
and move to a culture of customer-centric continuous improvement. Customer
focus and continuous improvement are the
two central pillars of business success.
Focus on improving your product, focus on
improving your marketing, focus on giving
your customers the experience they want.
What big-name companies can you think of
that are known for being
successful and dominating their chosen
market? Perhaps, you might come up with a
list of names like Sony, Apple, Hilton, or
Amazon. What do all companies have in
common? They place the customer
experience at the forefront of
everything they do. They focus on
providing the customer with the best
possible experience and they focus on
continually looking for ways to improve
that experience. Let's now go through a
case study to understand the importance
of continuous improvement and customer
focus. In the online world, Amazon are the
undisputed winners in the customer-centric
stakes. From the very beginning of the
company, they have always focused in on
the customer, always tried to do things
better than they were. This drive to put
the customer front and center has led
them to constantly improving every
detail of their site. You might think
that by now, they would have worked out
the best design for their website. But
they are still running more than 200
tests at any one time, constantly
striving to improve every aspect of
their operations. See how Amazon have
changed their website over the years,
always improving it one detail after
another. Focus for a moment on their "Add
to Cart" button. In the late 90s, the words
"you can always remove it later", appeared
by the bottom. They also included words
of reassurance, "safe" and "guaranteed". At
this time, internet shopping was still a
relatively new experience for many
people and they were keen to reassure
customers that their orders were safe
with Amazon. Later they removed some of
this wording and moved to Amazon
1-click. By this time, we were all a
lot more comfortable with buying online
and the focus for Amazon was more on
making the buying process as simple as
possible. Later still, Amazon introduced
Amazon Marketplace and were happy to
actually, let their conversion rate drop
a little bit, as they could increase
their revenue by selling used books. Now
it's highly profitable for them, no
stocks, no extra advertising, they just
earn a percentage as a broker between
the seller and the buyer. There is always
this balance or tension between
increasing your conversion rate and your
revenue,
and you have to know what the best mix
is for your business. Another important
principle of Conversion Optimization is
balancing your available resources. That
is what you have available to help in
your Conversion Optimization efforts. It
comes down to three types of things that
you will need if you're going to be able
to get anything done. You're going to
need resources, you can't use things you
don't have. So what do you have on hand
right now, that you can use to work on
Conversion Optimization? Invest whatever
you have, focus on whatever resources you
have on the problem, and don't worry for
now about what you don't have. You're
also going to need people. People are an
essential component of any Conversion
Optimization strategy. You need people to
identify the changes that need to happen
and you need people to make those
changes:
designers, copywriters, technical people,
they all play a part in the process. Then,
culture. What is your corporate culture
like? Will your approach to Conversion
Optimization make a difference on the
way your organization thinks? If you
become too focused on one area, it's
possible that your entire strategy could
become unstuck. It is common for everyone
to focus on traffic. There is the abiding
idea that the more traffic equals, more
sales. This is not necessarily the case,
you need to focus less on PPC and
driving traffic, and more on user
experience. Start conducting usability
studies, examine your copy, your analytics,
plan to offer a better on-site
experience. Don't worry so much about
things that are off your website like PPC,
focus your effort and your budget on
conversion rate. Remember, most websites
don't have a traffic problem, they need
to improve their conversion rate.
Improving the experience of those who
visit your site, can double your sales. If
you're really going to make progress
towards a coherent conversion
optimization strategy, then you will need
to consider three specific areas:
marketing, graphic design, copywriting,
creative resources,
and technical.
Someone within your organization will
have to take ownership of the Conversion
Optimization project and push it forward
in all of these areas. One of the
greatest dangers with their strategy is,
that it becomes the responsibility of
one department, one area of your company,
and people begin to work individually,
rather than as a team.
You must get everyone on board with what
you are doing and shift your corporate
culture, if you're going to make this
work. Everyone from marketing to the
creative people, the designers, copywriter,
the flash people, to those who copy and
paste code to your website to make the
changes you need, they all have to know
where this process is leading and what
the ultimate goal is. You need resources,
but most of all you need the process:
Plan, measure, improve, repeat. Visitors
come to your websites for a variety of
reasons. But they all have at least some
level of interest in you or your brand,
otherwise, they would not be there.
Once they reach your website, it is your
job to persuade them to buy. To do this,
you will need to think through your
persuasion architecture process, that is
the process you go through to persuade
someone to take the all important step
and actually buy from you. There are
three parts to this process, or rather
three questions that you will need to
ask: Who are we trying to persuade? It's
much easier to make a sale if you know
the person you are talking to. You know
what appeals to them and where their
interests lie. You can adapt your selling
approach to answer all the questions
that they are likely to have. What action
do we want them to take? You must be
clear about the actions you want your
reader to take: do you want them to
forward a link, buy something, subscribe
to your list, download something, it must
be a clearly defined path for them to
follow, not just in terms of big actions,
think of the micro-action level as well,
what action should they take on this
page and next page and next page, all the
way through from the landing page to
final conversion. What actions do they
want to take? People have a variety of
goals in view, when they reach your
website. You may want them to do one
thing, they may have a completely
different goal in view.
They are in control of the experience
they have on your website. They want to
accomplish a particular task, we must
help them to accomplish their task while
at the same time, helping them to take
the action we want them to take. In this
way, they will be a satisfied customer and we'll also achieve our goals. If you
know anything about human nature, then
you know that human beings are all
different. Some of us are more logical,
some are more emotional in the way we
respond to situations and the way we
gather and process information also
varies. Some of us are more spontaneous
in our actions, while others take a more
logical approach to the buying process.
This different approach to information
gathering can be seen in the way people
consume the information on your website.
Studies show that there are four unique
patterns of eye tracking over websites.
People that are more competitive, tend to
focus their gaze on the top of the page.
Those who are more methodical in nature,
will look at all of the different data
points on the page, study the page
navigation and see how everything is
connected. Then there are the spontaneous
type of people, these are attracted to
interaction, they like pictures of people,
they like to see what's going on. Finally,
there are the humanistic types, these
visitors are little more deliberate, more
emotionally involved with the page. Each
of these types of person is going to
approach a webpage differently, they are
all going to want to see different
things if you're going to persuade them
to buy from you. We need to work out the
goals of each of these different types of
visitors. And to help us do that, we
create personas, buying models to help us
determine what each customer wants to
achieve on your website. In addition to
these personality types, we can divide
your visitors into other groups as well.
There are people who know about your
company, compared to those who don't know
anything about your business and what
you can do. There are returning buyers
and new customers. They all start from
different levels of knowledge and have
varying expectations from your business.
There are also different ways visitors
reach your website, that can have
effects on how they feel about your
business and what they are expecting
from you. So we could segment your
visitors by those who arrived by a PPC,
and those who came to you from social
media. We can make the segmentation as
simple or as complex as we wish.
The object is to help us create the
content for each of these groups of
people needed to complete the sale. We
need to build empathy with them. To do
this, we will be testing every aspect of
your web page. There are tools that can
help you do this. The Analytics Content
Experiments in Google Analytics allows
you to test every element on your page
and see if it will appeal more to
competitive or methodical personality
types.
Tools like this can be useful and will
help you make important decisions about
which elements to include in your
webpages. You can't change every aspect
of your website at once, or you won't
know which changes affected your
conversion rate. Start small, one change
at a time. This is the power of this tool.
5% may not be much, and it only takes a
few hours a month to get to that point.
But compounded over a 12-month period by
the end of the year, you will have
increased your conversion rate by more
than 80%. The key to reaching this
point is, to focus on improving your
corporate metabolism. No single perch is
going to achieve your long-term goals, it
must become a way of life for everyone
at your business. Constantly seizing your
opportunities and increasing your market
share
step by step, this process works, the
question is, will you work the process
and achieve your goals? In this lesson, we
have seen that Conversion Optimization
is about making small incremental
changes to your website over time. We
have said that optimization is an
ongoing process, not something that you
do once and then leave. You have learned
that there are different approaches to
information gathering and above all, we
have seen the importance of being
customer-centric in every area of your
operation.